<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the Irish Protestants in relation to recognising, or swearing allegiance to, and praying for King William and Queen Mary, stated and resolved.</title>
            <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1490A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229883</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899316</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899316</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153025</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96259)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153025)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2340:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the Irish Protestants in relation to recognising, or swearing allegiance to, and praying for King William and Queen Mary, stated and resolved.</title>
                  <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Clavel, and are to be sold by John North, bookseller in Dublin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XCI. [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Wettenhall by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Dublin, Ireland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Loyalty --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153025:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF THE <hi>Iriſh Proteſtants:</hi> In Relation to RECOGNISING, OR Swearing ALLEGIANCE to, And PRAYING for King WILLIAM and Queen MARY, Stated and Reſolved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>John North,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Dublin.</hi> M DC XC I.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153025:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153025:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THE following Paper contains the Reſult of a certain Perſons Thoughts, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſince, when he, being cut off from the uſual means of <hi>conſulting with others,</hi> could only enter into a <hi>Conſultation with himſelf,</hi> for <hi>reſolving his own Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no <hi>mans ſin</hi> ſimply to <hi>doubt,</hi> but it is <hi>every mans buſineſs</hi> to endeavor his own <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction:</hi> and 'tis <hi>ſome mens Duty</hi> to <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie others</hi> beſides themſelves.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>this number,</hi> becauſe the Author took himſelf to be, he <hi>communicated</hi> theſe his Thoughts to <hi>ſuch</hi> for whom he was <hi>concern'd:</hi> and 'tis at their Promotion if they now go further.</p>
            <p>In his Arguing he choſe for Satisfaction to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed rather on Foundations of <hi>Divinity,</hi> than <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy</hi> and <hi>Law:</hi> little meddling with thoſe Grounds,
<pb facs="tcp:153025:3"/> on which, ſince the Writing hereof, he finds abler Heads most to build. He is very content to leave each Man to his own Province, and only deſires he may not be cenſured, as too ignorant, for keeping ſo cloſe within what he apprehends to be his. It is indeed herein he finds moſt ſolid Content, Reſolution and Repoſe of Mind.</p>
            <p>God make all of us Sincere, Humble, Satisfied, and if not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous, yet at leaſt Peaceable and Quiet.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 27. 1690.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153025:3"/>
            <head>THE CASE OF THE IRISH PROTESTANTS: In Relation to RECOGNISING King WILLIAM and Queen MARY, STATED and RESOLVED.</head>
            <p n="1">I. FOR the due <hi>Stating,</hi> and ſo more ſatisfactory <hi>Reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> this our <hi>Caſe,</hi> it will be neceſſary to conſider in the beginning, <hi>what Recognition</hi> of theſe Princes, or of their Sovereignty, is either <hi>expreſly,</hi> or <hi>by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, required</hi> of us; and then <hi>what Barrs</hi> there lie <hi>in Conſcience,</hi> to our making ſuch Recognition.</p>
            <p n="2">II, THERE can be no doubt, but it is <hi>intended,</hi> that we ſhould receive and ſubmit to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as perfectly and intirely, as ever by Law we ſubmitted to, or owned any of our late Sovereigns. And I muſt add, we <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>Ireland,</hi> have <hi>all the Reaſon</hi> in the World, even from our own <hi>Intereſt</hi> to do it, with <hi>more Zeal,</hi> and <hi>Paſſion,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153025:4"/> than we did to either of their immediate Predeceſſors. But all the <hi>Recognition,</hi> which, as far as yet to me appears, is <hi>expreſly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> from any, is, only to take an <hi>Oath of Fidelity</hi> to them, and to <hi>pray for them as King and Queen,</hi> and perhaps as our <hi>Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> from Oppreſſion. Now that <hi>Oath,</hi> as I am informed, is pen'd in a <hi>ſhorter, eaſier,</hi> and <hi>milder Form,</hi> than any of our Oaths of Allegiance in the Reigns of our former Kings. Thus it is ſaid to run:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I do ſwear to bear Faith and true Allegiance to King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary.</p>
            <p>The very <hi>penning</hi> of this Oath ſhews the <hi>Tenderneſs, Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Temper of theſe great Princes.</hi> For there is <hi>nothing</hi> therein <hi>Dogmatical,</hi> (if I may uſe that Term) of which Nature was the greater part, and moſt of the Paragraphs of the former Oath, but only a <hi>Sacred Promiſe</hi> of (what is needful) <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>true Allegiance.</hi> Which tho (I ſay) it be moſt certainly intended, it ſhould be <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>plenary,</hi> (and according to the Intention of the Impoſer muſt every Oath be underſtood by them that take it, elſe there is Fallacy and Equivocation therein) yet as to each Man's ſecret Sentiments there is by theſe <hi>indefinite Terms</hi> much <hi>left</hi> to the <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> of every individual Subject, what the particulars of that Faith and true Allegiance are. A <hi>Temper</hi> not obſerved in the penning the former Oaths of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance or Supremacy.</p>
            <p n="3">III. THE <hi>Barrs in Conſcience,</hi> which any I think can pretend to againſt ſuch Recognition are, <hi>Oaths</hi> formerly taken, and a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognition</hi> made of <hi>James</hi> II. who is yet alive; and the <hi>Bond</hi> with which <hi>Holy Scriptures tie</hi> all <hi>Oaths</hi> upon our <hi>Conſciences</hi> and Practice, yea, tho ſomewhat unadviſedly and prejudicially made, even to <hi>our own Hurt and Damage.</hi> The Oaths, I think, which can ſtick upon any are chiefly Two, The <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> and of <hi>Supremacy.</hi> Yet there is alſo, if I miſtake not beſides theſe, what ſome called the <hi>Short Oath, [Not to take up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King or any Commiſſioned by him,] impoſed</hi> on the Members of moſt <hi>Corporations</hi> in this Kingdom, as I have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153025:4"/> been informed, of late days. However, there is a <hi>Declaration</hi> in theſe Words, <hi>ſubſcribed</hi> and <hi>publickly read,</hi> or recogniſed, <hi>In Sacris,</hi> by all the <hi>Conforming Clergy</hi> of the three Kingdoms, in ſo ſolemn a manner, that it was even upon them equivalent to a moſt ſolemn Oath. The <hi>Recognition</hi> is that made in the late (pretended) <hi>Iriſh Parliament (May</hi> 7. 1689,) and paſt in form of an Act, penned, I confeſs, with all the Weight and Emphaſis, which, I think, either proper or improper Language could put into it. Now that the Reſolutions of all Doubts ariſing from any of theſe, may be as diſtinct, as the Brevity deſigned, will permit, we will conſider each ſeverally. And if in the end it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that in our preſent Circumſtances there lies no Obligation upon us, to <hi>James</hi> II. from any of theſe Ties, then we may with ſafe Conſcience perform what is required.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. AND firſt, for the <hi>Oath of Allegiance.</hi> This Oath <hi>was lawful</hi> and <hi>wholeſome</hi> enough, and <hi>in former Reigns,</hi> even <hi>to Proteſtants poſſible</hi> to be kept; and alſo <hi>Obligatory.</hi> But there are <hi>three</hi> things which <hi>wholly take off</hi> our being obliged by it to King <hi>James.</hi> Firſt, <hi>he the ſaid King James</hi> II. has made it to us <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</hi> Secondly, <hi>God and King James</hi> have made it at preſent <hi>impoſſible.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>we in Ireland</hi> are <hi>formally releaſed</hi> from it, perhaps by <hi>Law;</hi> I am ſure in <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Equity.</hi> Now if any one of theſe three be true, the Obligation thereof to King <hi>James</hi> is diſcharged: much more, if all.</p>
            <p n="5">V. FIRST, I ſay, <hi>King James</hi> II. has <hi>made</hi> it to us who are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, <hi>unlawful</hi> to pay him ſuch Allegiance, as was due to his Predeceſſors, and would have been due to him, by virtue of that Oath, had he trod in his Predeceſſors Steps. His Predeceſſors, ſince the framing this Form of Oath, went not about to <hi>ſubject the Imperial Crown</hi> and Dignity of the three Kingdoms (as <hi>King James</hi> has done, <hi>eſpecially that of</hi> Ireland, with a Witneſs) to the Power of any Foreign Prince or Potentate, no not of the Pope himſelf. Which for a Subject to do (for of Princes we will not ſpeak) is <hi>unlawful, and Treaſon by our Laws.</hi> We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153025:5"/> therefore <hi>with all our might aſſiſt and defend ſuch a King,</hi> which yet in the Oath of Allegiance we ſeem to have ſworn to do, becauſe by this aſſiſtance we are guilty of contributing to the higheſt Breach of our Laws; we commit Treaſon againſt the Crown: And there being no Acceſſories in Treaſon, I will not ſay in what danger we ſhould be in a Proteſtant Succeſſors Reign.</p>
            <p>But there is more yet in the Caſe. It is <hi>unlawful by the Law of God,</hi> for a Proteſtant People to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and defend in the Exerciſe and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of Regal Power ſuch a King as <hi>James</hi> II. has made and carried himſelf: for they could not thereby but mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly contribute, and put their Hands, not only to the <hi>deſtroying their own, but their Proteſtant Fellow Subjects Eſtates, Liberties</hi> and <hi>Lives,</hi> and what is more, their <hi>Common Religion</hi> too. <note n="*" place="inline">The proof of theſe Particulars by ſome Hiſtorical Inſtances, in the Treatment which the poor <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants found from thoſe in Power under the late King, would caſt ſuch <hi>Odium</hi> on more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps than were guilty, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perſuade my ſelf to ſet it down: and poſſibly it is ſo notorius, that I need not. Enough has fallen from my Pen in the Sequel, through a kind of Impotency, or too tender Senſe of what I have ſeen,</note> If it be ſaid, the <hi>King promiſed</hi> to maintain us in the Profeſſion of our Religion, and Poſſeſſion of our Eſtates, Liberties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He did indeed ſo <hi>promiſe,</hi> and I believe, of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at firſt <hi>intended</hi> it: But he had <hi>put the Power</hi> of all into ſuch Mens hands, thar he <hi>could not perform</hi> what he had promiſed. Were not our <hi>Rights,</hi> our <hi>Lands,</hi> our <hi>Goods,</hi> and our <hi>Churches</hi> themſelves taken from us, <hi>contrary,</hi> not only <hi>to his Promiſes,</hi> but <hi>Proclamations?</hi> And which of any of theſe (eſpecially our Churches) tho upon his expreſs Command, under his Hand and Seal, was ever reſtored? What can be expected from him, who firſt <hi>incapacitates</hi> himſelf to <hi>perform,</hi> and then <hi>makes fair Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes?</hi> Did not the <hi>Iriſh Act of Attainder debar</hi> the King of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative to <hi>pardon</hi> thoſe which it made Criminals and Traitors (contrary to the Law of Nature, that common Teſt of Equity, ſo much appealed to by ſome in the late <hi>Iriſh</hi> Houſe of Lords,) for flying merely to preſerve their Lives, or ſecuring themſelves from <hi>Iriſh</hi> Mercy, that is, from—what I will not ſay. Nor will I inſiſt upon, what I might add and aggravate: By the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and <hi>Laws of the Religion he profeſſes,</hi> he either <hi>had ſworn to</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153025:5"/> 
               <hi>deſtroy</hi> (or <hi>ought</hi> to have ſworn to deſtroy) both <hi>us and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> And when Men firſt <hi>ſwear to do</hi> a thing, and then <hi>promiſe not to do it,</hi> and <hi>capacitate</hi> themſelves <hi>to perform their Oaths,</hi> but <hi>incapacitate themſelves to perform their Promiſes,</hi> which can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſhould take place, the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> or the <hi>Oath?</hi> I may ſafely avow in behalf of the Proteſtants of the three Kingdoms, there is not a conſcientious Man amongſt us, would ever have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from King <hi>James</hi> even our <hi>Active Obedience,</hi> could we have <hi>ſecured</hi> our <hi>Religion and good Conſcience</hi> by active Adheſion to him. I will add alſo, becauſe in my Conſcience I believe it; had not the ſecuring the Proteſtant Religion, more forcibly moved the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> than the Ambition of a Throne, he would never have attempted ſo <hi>ſpeedy a Succeſſion.</hi> In a Word, we did obey as far as God's Command goes; Gods Command is with Limitation. <hi>Obey in the Lord;</hi> we did ſo. We did obey as long, and as far, as was lawful, and that is as far as any Oath can bind us, for to an unlawful Act no Oath can bind. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod's Oath</hi> did not bind him to cut off S. <hi>John Baptiſt's Head;</hi> nor can our Oaths oblige us to be Aſſiſtants, and aiding to the cutting off the Heads of innocent Proteſtant Peers, or hanging up ſuch Commons; and to the diſarming, and putting out of Power, all Proteſtants, and arming and advancing all Papiſts, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying our ſelves, Neighbors and Religion. This is unlawful by the Law of God.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. I might here, inſtead of ſaying King <hi>James</hi> has made the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance due to him by this Oath <hi>unlawful</hi> for Proteſtants to pay, have ſaid (perhaps with more Propriety of Speech) he has made the <hi>Oath as to him void and null.</hi> For all his Subjects, who took it, were ſuppoſed by Law to ſwear to a <hi>Legal King,</hi> that is, to a King who would govern according to Law, and protect his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and their Rights, as by his Oath and Law bound. Such a King the Oath was deſign'd to: and actually to ſuch a King we ſwore Allegiance. But ſuch, <hi>King James</hi> did not pleaſe to be. Wherefore by this Oath no Allegiance is due to him. But I thought, this <hi>notion</hi> might ſeem to ſome more <hi>ſubtile,</hi> and the <hi>proof</hi> of it might, as above ſuggeſted, have been <hi>more odious</hi> than
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153025:6"/> the other. Each comes much to the ſame final iſſue: for accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to either the Obligation ceaſeth, as concluded; and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may take in his Candor which he pleaſes. To proceed then.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. GOD has made it to us the <hi>Iriſh Proteſtants,</hi> here at leaſt, <hi>morally impoſſible</hi> to perform to King <hi>James</hi> the Duty which in the Oath of Allegiance we ſwore: Therefore the Obligation of that Oath ceaſeth as to him, or which is the ſame, we are not bound to him by that Oath. I doubt not but that our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries will ſay, <hi>defending the Perſon and Poſſeſſion of a King by force of Arms,</hi> to be a <hi>point of Allegiance.</hi> I ſay we are here by God's Providence unable to defend King <hi>James</hi> by Arms in the Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Crown. Not to mention, that it is not long ſince our Roman Catholick Adverſaries, by King <hi>James</hi>'s Orders (as they ſaid) took away our Arms from us; (and ſurely we are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd for not being in Arms for a King, who would not ſuffer us to bear Arms) God has now put us under the Power of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond William the Conqueror,</hi> whom I muſt affirm (beſides his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, more ways than one, otherwiſe juſtly intitle'd) to have <hi>a Right to our Allegiance by Conqueſt;</hi> that which gave the King of <hi>England</hi> the firſt (and ſtill avowed) Title to <hi>Ireland.</hi> I do averr us in <hi>Ireland conquered,</hi> and with my Heart bleſs God for it. For beſides our being thereby <hi>delivered (intirely</hi> and <hi>finally</hi> I hope) <hi>from Popery,</hi> we are delivered alſo, if we attend thereto, from <hi>all Scruple,</hi> which would ſtick in us touching the Will of God as to our Subjection to our new King: For we cannot doubt but that we <hi>ought to be ſubject to them, whom God has ſet over us.</hi> And when by his Providence, he ſo plainly <hi>pulls down one,</hi> and <hi>ſets up another,</hi> we <hi>cannot doubt,</hi> who it is whom he has ſet over us. If ſtill any will doubt, I demand of them, what ſhould a van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd Multitude, what ſhould Men, Women and Children, brought under Subjection do? Muſt they all dye Martyrs for the Title of a Prince, who would not preſerve their Rights by Law and Peace, and through the hand of God has not been able to defend his own or theirs by War? Do not the <hi>Iriſh Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> who blame us moſt, daily <hi>make Conditions for themſelves,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153025:6"/> and ſhall it be unlawful for us to do the ſame? The great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt them and us, as to our preſent Circumſtances, is, <hi>They</hi> were <hi>conquered with their Swords in their hands; We,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>their Priſoners,</hi> perhaps they may think Slaves and Properties, as it has been too plain to us they would have uſed us. But this is in our favor: For it appears hereby, thoſe who were <hi>their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors</hi> were <hi>our Deliverers;</hi> and if it be lawful in this caſe for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to accept of Terms, 'tis our duty to be thankful to God that there are thoſe now come, who can give Terms both to them and us.</p>
            <p>This Plea ſufficiently juſtifies us <hi>Iriſh Proteſtants</hi> againſt any poſſible Imputation to us from our <hi>Iriſh Adverſaries</hi> in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. And as to our <hi>Engliſh Friends,</hi> we will ſuppoſe them more ſenſible of our Condition, than that before them we ought to make Apologies, when in our Conſciences we want none.</p>
            <p>But as to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> let me tell them farther, no imaginary free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of theirs can now in Conſcience exempt them from this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. The <hi>People of the Jews,</hi> the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> were <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in bondage to any</hi> (as free born a People certainly as <hi>Iriſh</hi> Men can be) yet when God put them under the Yoke of <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnazzar,</hi> his command by the Prophet (encouraged too by a bleſſing annext) is <hi>ſerve the King of</hi> Babylon <hi>and Live.</hi> The ſame which God ſpeaks now by the Voice of his Providence to the Natives of this Kingdom, in as much as he has left nothing elſe poſſible to them: They muſt therefore be ſubject <hi>not only for Wrath, but Conſcience ſake,</hi> and for Men to ſwear to do what is their duty to do, cannot certainly be unlawful.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. FURTHER, not only <hi>God,</hi> but even King <hi>James</hi> II. has <hi>made it impoſſible</hi> to his Proteſtant Subjects to keep the Oath of Allegiance to him. For that Oath expreſly (as well as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordinarily taken by many of us, (I mean the Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy) obliges all who have taken it, not only to defend to the uttermoſt of their power <hi>His Majeſties Perſon, Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors,</hi> but both <hi>His and Their Crown and Dignity.</hi> Which Crown and Dignity ſignifie (as the Oath of Supremacy, and ſo the Law
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153025:7"/> interprets thoſe Terms) <hi>all Juriſdictions, Preeminences and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, granted or belonging to the Kings Highneſs, his Heirs or Succeſſors, or united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm,</hi> that is of <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Crown of England</hi> ſaith our Law is <hi>Imperial,</hi> and ſubject to no Prince on Earth; but only unto God: If therefore a <hi>Prince</hi> will <hi>ſubject his Crown,</hi> and ſo his <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> to a <hi>Foreign Power,</hi> and eſpecially to that Power, which has now theſe ſeveral Ages inceſſantly and indefatigably, by all means within its Sphere, ſtudied and endeavor'd the Ruin of them, and the Extirpation of their Religion, <hi>I mean to the Pope of Rome,</hi> it <hi>becomes impoſſible</hi> for the <hi>Subjects of ſuch a King,</hi> at once (or toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to the uttermoſt of their power to defend <hi>His Perſon, and His Heirs and Succeſſors, His and Their Crown and Dignity.</hi> The <hi>Kingdom of England</hi> (of which by Law and Preſcription <hi>Ireland</hi> is a Branch and dependent) has ever been avowed, and to this day is, a <hi>Free Kingdom:</hi> But how Tributary and enſlaved it would become, by being again ſubjected to the Papacy, I liſt not to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate; yet cannot but in ſhort take notice that the <hi>Heir,</hi> by the Subjects defending and maintaining ſuch a King Poſſeſſor, <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of his Power and Rights:</hi> and <hi>ſo doth the Crown of its Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Preeminence</hi> and <hi>Authority.</hi> In ſuch caſe therefore a Man can no more keep this Oath, than he can <hi>reconcile Contradictions;</hi> which even the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Divines ordinarily Teach, is not in the power of Omnipotence. And ſuch is the Caſe between <hi>James</hi> II. and all the Proteſtants of theſe Three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>But it was <hi>worſe</hi> with the <hi>Poor Iriſh Proteſtants,</hi> than with the reſt of the People of any of his Majeſties Dominions. <hi>We,</hi> though moſt of us <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> were not only ſubjected to <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> but to the moſt inveterate of them, <hi>Iriſh Roman Catholicks,</hi> (Enemies to us on other ſcores beſides our Religion) contrary to the <hi>expreſs Laws</hi> of both Kingdoms in this behalf, contrary to the manifeſt <hi>Intereſt of the Heir,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Honor and Dignity of the Crown of England;</hi> from which as far as an Act of an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament could do the feat, this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> was by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute (ſolemnly paſt in that their Parliament above mentioned) in effect actually ſeparated and diſunited. The Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153025:7"/> was hereby to loſe the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> a very conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Emolument</hi> certainly as well as <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction.</hi> Theſe things are notorious matter of Fact, and ſo publickly manifeſt, that they cannot be denied.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not of being ſubjected to a <hi>French Government, and Governors;</hi> of our being enforced to ſupplicate many times for our Liberties and Lives, (I am ſure for the ſupports of our Lives, the eating the Bread, and wearing the poor Clothes, which of our own were left us; and ſome of us directly for our Lives, even in Caſes wherein we were Offenders againſt no Law of God or of Man, Military or Civil) I ſpeak not I ſay of our being neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thus to ſupplicate to Governors of a Foreign Nation and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, who could not underſtand us when addreſſing to them in our own Speech, and would not underſtand our Interpreters in theirs. I ſpeak not of <hi>Pacts and Sales,</hi> (of which great Evidence, as to this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or a great part of it, might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) nor of other like or more odious things; as deſignedly avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that might exaſperate ſome Men, or together immoderately aggravate others Guilt as well as our Oppreſſions. But it is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as clear as the Sun, that if there could be degrees in natural Impoſſibilities, there lay the <hi>higheſt natural Impoſſibility</hi> on all (but eſpecially the <hi>Iriſh) Proteſtants,</hi> in the Circumſtances they were in, to <hi>keep this Oath:</hi> and that not by any fault of their own; for they were caſt into this impoſſibility by the Prince, to whom, by that Oath, Allegiance was, or was to have been due. Now foraſmuch as no one can be bound to that which is impoſſible, of all Men, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants ſtand not, by the Oath of Allegiance, bound to defend the Perſon of <hi>James</hi> II. in his or their preſent Circumſtances.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. IF it ſhould be ſaid by any, <hi>Theſe Pleas</hi> can only <hi>diſcharge</hi> Subjects of ſo <hi>much Allegiance</hi> as can be proved <hi>unlawful</hi> or <hi>impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> but they ſhall ſtill ſtand <hi>obliged</hi> to <hi>what is lawful and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, I allow it for truth: and together Avow,</hi> that <hi>notwithſtanding our Performance of what either or both</hi> the fore-mentioned <hi>Branches</hi> of Recognition by the preſent King and Queen <hi>required</hi> of us do
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153025:8"/> contain, We both <hi>may,</hi> and I doubt not all conſiderative conſcientious Perſons within theſe Kingdoms <hi>Do,</hi> bear and <hi>pay all lawful parts,</hi> or Inſtances of <hi>Duty</hi> to our late King. And principally what the Article of King <hi>John's Magna Charta</hi> in ſuch Caſe as this exacts: <hi>The Safety of the Perſons of the King and Queen, and of their Children,</hi> we look upon as moſt religiouſly inviolable. None of us would attempt, or conſent to any attempt, upon their Sacred Perſons.</p>
            <p>There is indeed a <hi>Child in Controverſie,</hi> touching which it muſt at leaſt be confeſt what a moſt zealous and conſtant adherent of King <hi>James</hi>'s (the ſame too if I miſtake not, more than once in great Power and Truſt under him) has not doubted to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to the World. <q>The buſineſs of the <hi>Prince of Wales</hi> has been ſo carried, as if thoſe, whom it moſt concerns that it ſhould be true, had not had a mind it ſhould be believed,</q> [or words to that effect, for I have not the Paper by me: 'tis intitled <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands Criſis.</hi>] It is to me an ungrateful task to give ſuch Deſcant, or Illuſtration, to this ingenuous Acknowledgment, as the Caſe requires: but inſtead thereof I muſt be ſo faithful to my own ſenſe as to add, That the Perſons moſt concerned for the Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of that Child, have now ſo farther managed the matter, that I ſee not how its <hi>Legitimacy</hi> is <hi>poſſible</hi> ever to be made out to the <hi>Publick Satisfaction</hi> of theſe Nations. Wherefore, in my Apprehenſion, it muſt remain a doubt till the day ſhall come, that ſhall open all things. In the mean time, being there is the <hi>ſame Reaſon</hi> of things <hi>not in being,</hi> and of things <hi>not apparent,</hi> no Man can forfeit his Allegiance, for not being ſollicitous for the preſervation of this Child: eſpecially now it is removed out of the Sphere of our Defence, as well as Knowledge.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>any other part of Allegiance</hi> imaginable, in the preſent Juncture, lawful or poſſible, it would be conſidered in ſpecial what the Particulars are. Our <hi>Counſel</hi> would never be taken, and we have been declared again and again not to be truſted; yea and (notwithſtanding the utmoſt fidelity of many of us) reviled and treated as ſuch. As to our <hi>Prayers,</hi> what it is not lawful for us to endeavor, it is not lawful for us to pray for. But
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153025:8"/> it has been ſhewn King <hi>James</hi> has made it unlawful for us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him in his Poſſeſſion and Exerciſe of his Regal Power: And to bring him back thereto, as far as human Prudence (I think) can ſee, were but to bring our Religion and its Profeſſors under the ſame Yoke, Opreſſions and danger of Extinction, under which we ſo lately groaned: therefore this it is unlawful to pray for. As far as we may lawfully pray for him, we own we do: nor is it inconſiſtent with the Prayers required of us for King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> Amongſt thoſe who <hi>Err</hi> and are <hi>Deceived,</hi> amongſt <hi>Our Enemies, Perſecutors, and Slanderers,</hi> whom we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God to have mercy on, to <hi>forgive them and turn their Hearts,</hi> by <hi>way of Eminency,</hi> we tacitly compriſe our late King. In ſecret alſo, perhaps by name, we further pray, That God would take from him all Ignorance, hardneſs of Heart and contempt of his Word, and to bring him home to Chriſt's Flock, that he may be ſaved amongſt the remnant of the true <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> To do this for him by <hi>Name in publick,</hi> would be looked upon as Affront and publick Reproach: To do it in ſecret, as it is Prudent Charity, ſo it is a Loyalty we diſown not. Thus <hi>Samuel mourned for Saul,</hi> even when <hi>God had rejected him,</hi> and it <hi>repented the Lord that he had made him King.</hi> And beyond what I have thus openly and freely ſpecified, I acknowledge I ſee not any part of Loyalty and Devotion left lawful or poſſible to us <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of King <hi>James</hi> II. except any would have added a <hi>ſublime degree of Civil Honor,</hi> (the ſaluting or ſerving him upon the Knee, or ſuch like) of which together with a <hi>Revenue</hi> ample enough to maintain a Court, I think there ought to be no diſpute; but none of theſe interfere with the Recognition required.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Now to return from Objections, and to proceed with what was above propounded. Laſtly, it is to be ſaid for the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who now are (at leaſt who all along theſe Troubles <hi>remained) in Ireland,</hi> they are as fully and directly <hi>Releaſed</hi> from this Oath, at leaſt from that part of Allegiance, Defending King <hi>James</hi> by force of Arms, as <hi>Reaſon, Equity,</hi> or even <hi>Expreſs Law</hi> can be well conceived to releaſe them. In
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153025:9"/> all <hi>Civil Othas,</hi> if the <hi>Power impoſing the Oath,</hi> and to whom the Oath is made, <hi>ſhall releaſe</hi> the Obligees, ſuch Obligees are diſcharged of their Oath, and reduced to their firſt Liberty. Now I ſay we (the People before ſpecified) were <hi>three ways re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed,</hi> either from the <hi>whole Oath,</hi> or at leaſt from <hi>this part of it,</hi> which ſome expect we ſhould own our ſelves bound to, of <hi>fighting for King James</hi> II.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>whole Oath of Allegiance,</hi> Summer was twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>month, by King and Parliament, (a Parliament at leaſt whoſe Authority and Legitimacy our Adverſaries will not impeach) was in this Kingdom by expreſs Statute <hi>repealed;</hi> under the Name (if my memory fail not) of the <hi>New Oath of Allegiance.</hi> And whereas ſome Peers (upon Reaſons which are not needful here to be inſerted) ſtood againſt the Repeal of it, and one excepted againſt that ſtyle, <hi>The New Oath of Allegiance,</hi> the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was returned by them who ruled, aſſigning the Reign, in which that Oath of Allegiance was made; a point wherein the Objector was not at all ignorant, as I take it, but I am ſure was born ſome Ages, at leaſt, a long Age, and upwards, ſince that Reign, and ſo never took any elder, and (I am as confident) never any Newer or Later Oath of Allegiance to King <hi>James.</hi> Wherefore being by this Repeal releaſed from that Oath of Allegiance, and having never taken any other, ſuch <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants as I ſpeak of, are under no Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to King <hi>James</hi> the Second, and that through his own and his <hi>Dear Roman Catholick Parliaments</hi> Act. Which being, I think, the only Service they did us, we ought not, but <hi>with thanks,</hi> to <hi>acknowledge,</hi> and <hi>record</hi> it to Poſterity: tho what Service thereby they did THEIR King (as appropriating him to themſelves they uſed to call him) we muſt leave him and them together at their leiſure to conſider.</p>
            <p>Again we <hi>Iriſh Proteſtants</hi> were not only <hi>diſarmed,</hi> as above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, but by iterated Proclamations <hi>interdicted,</hi> to have any kind of <hi>Arms</hi> in our <hi>Houſes,</hi> tho merely for the <hi>Defence</hi> of them <hi>from Thieves and Robbers:</hi> and that under <hi>divers Forfeitures,</hi> which in each <hi>later Proclamation</hi> were ſtill made <hi>ſeverer,</hi> and in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153025:9"/> the end, as I remember, the <hi>Penalty</hi> was no leſs, than being proceeded againſt as <hi>Traitors.</hi> How far theſe Proclamations were executed upon many innocent perſons, in City, and in Country, by ſuch, who, coming into our Houſes to ſearch for Arms, could eaſily find what themſelves had hid, I have no mind to ſpeak: But certainly King <hi>James</hi>'s forbidding us ſo ſtrictly, to wear or have Arms, was on his part a Diſcharge to us from the uſe of them, tho in his Defence. For what it was <hi>Treaſon</hi> for us <hi>to Have,</hi> how could it be <hi>Allegiance</hi> or <hi>Duty</hi> for us <hi>to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, it muſt not be omitted here, what is with the greateſt Aſſurance reported by Multitudes, even of our Adverſaries, that upon the late Defeat at the <hi>Boyn,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> himſelf told his <hi>Iriſh</hi> Commanders, then about him: <q>He ſaw their Men would not ſtand, and they had nothing to do to think of conteſting with ſuch an Army, as was againſt them; commanded too by ſuch a Prince for their General. He therefore adviſed them to ſhift for themſelves, as, he ſaid, he would do [and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed did] and to make the beſt Terms they could for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</q> The ſame in effect, as is teſtified by many, he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards repeated at his paſſage through <hi>Dublin;</hi> and 'tis plain he <hi>confirmed</hi> theſe his Sentiments by his <hi>practice.</hi> Now what was ſaid to them, we cannot but take as (implicitly at leaſt) reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and extending it ſelf to <hi>all his People in</hi> Ireland, then in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to him; as I am ſure were we, touching whom the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conſultation proceeds: Wherefore we were then releaſed amongſt others, and left to our ſelves, to make Terms; and the Conqueror allowing us no other Terms but theſe, we are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by this Releaſe (if we had not been ſo before) at liberty to embrace and accept them.</p>
            <p>We have then thus done with the Oaths of Allegiance and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, together with the Obligation of them both, as to King <hi>James</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. IT follows we proceeed to the <hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Not taking up Arms againſt the King, or any Perſons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153025:10"/> 
               <hi>by him,</hi> extant in the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> (Anno Dom. 1662.) and either taken or ſubſcribed and avowed pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly by very many of us. Touching this, I will not ſay what I have heard ſome Learned in our Laws have ſaid, that this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration is not to be found in the Original record of that ſtatute IN TERMINIS as in our Books, but has been corruptly and ſurreptitiouſly inſerted (as it ſtands) into the Printed Copy. If this be true, it was an abominable Wrong and Impoſition on the Subject; and upon whom to be charged I will not ſpeak, nor ſo much as ſuffer my ſelf to gueſs. But certainly it would in ſuch caſe much take off from the Obligation of that Oath or Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that it ſhould be ſo fraudulently and illegally impoſed. <hi>My Anſwer</hi> then <hi>is;</hi> I conceive <hi>Moſt,</hi> I might have ſaid <hi>all Iriſh Proteſtants</hi> have <hi>little to do</hi> wirh <hi>this Oath</hi> in the preſent juncture. For either we are <hi>already in Arms,</hi> or <hi>Not.</hi> Thoſe of us who are <hi>already in Arms,</hi> cannot but be preſum'd to be <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lawfulneſs of that War, wherein we now are engaged, and are not <hi>after Vows to make Enquiry.</hi> To me truly <hi>the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> ſeems <hi>eaſie:</hi> For a Commiſſion contrary to Law (as are all Commiſſions of late years granted, or in preſent being to <hi>R. Catholicks)</hi> is by Law no Commiſſion, and conſequently the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who bear it <hi>not commiſſionated</hi> but <hi>private men,</hi> or rather while they Act purſuant to ſuch Commiſſions, <hi>Publick Robbers;</hi> which point juſtified all that roſe againſt <hi>Tyrconnell,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther R. Catholicks in this Kingdom pretending to Commiſſions from K. <hi>James.</hi> And if K. <hi>James</hi> would put himſelf at the head of ſuch a body to countenance, and abet them, I do not ſee how his preſence (even if he had been in full poſſeſſion of his Crown) could give them more Authority; Since he could onely thereby make himſelf leſs a Legal King, not them more Legal Officers. And the ſame thing (if there were no more) ſtill juſtifies thoſe who now fight againſt them that act in his name: Not to ſpeak that K. <hi>James</hi> has otherwiſe here <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n King'd</hi> himſelf; for certainly a King, which <hi>releaſes his Subjects</hi> of their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> as we have ſhewn him to have done, is <hi>no longer their King.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:153025:10"/>
            <p> Thoſe who are <hi>not yet in Arms,</hi> if they have any ſcruple, for which I profeſs I ſee no reaſon, may forbear taking Arms in that Cauſe, wherein they are not ſatisfied. I do not ſee any compulſory means uſed to bring them into Arms. It is <hi>not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired</hi> of us all <hi>to fight,</hi> but all of us are to promiſe to be quiet and to pray for our Protectors, which certainly all may do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out touching on any thing in that (whether) Oath or Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wherefore in our preſent condition theſe alſo are out of Doors.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. WE are in the next place to conſider the <hi>Recognition,</hi> which was made perſonally of <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> in the late (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi> As to which parliamentary Act (be it what it can be) it muſt be ſaid, <hi>No Iriſh Proteſtant,</hi> even of thoſe few that were preſent in either Houſe, are <hi>accomptable</hi> for the very Body and Frame of it, much leſs for every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Expreſſion or even Clauſe therein. It was the firſt Act that was paſt, and truly precipitated. It was not admitted to any due debate (at leaſt in the Lords houſe) and ſome who in the end earneſtly deſired the alteration but of one Expreſſion, which was apprehended to be improper Language, could not ſpeed therein. Now thoſe who would not at our importunity, alter their ſtyle, would not for our ſakes have waved any of their fundamental materials, of which they were much more fond. What <hi>Perpetual dread</hi> and <hi>Moral Force,</hi> all the proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant members were under, I am very unwilling, if not unable, to ſpeak. It ſufficiently ſpeaks for them, that as many of them as by their quality were capacitated to proteſt, <hi>did proteſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the more Momentous Acts that paſſed, this haply be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing excepted, againſt which they had no time well to think, much leſs to form a Proteſt: the Act being firſt brought in to the Houſe of Lords, there read haſtily three times (for Forms ſake rather than otherwiſe) and, to the beſt of my memory, immediately ſent down to the Commons, and never by the Proteſtant Lords heard of again, till brought in for the Royal Aſſent. Beſides this, having been all along kept <hi>in the dark,</hi> the Proteſtants there
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153025:11"/> 
               <hi>knew not</hi> on what bottom, or in what poſture, things ſtood in <hi>England,</hi> (a <hi>Regency</hi> and many ſuch Expedients were whiſpered up and down.) Nor had they had experience, how a <hi>Royal Catholick</hi> would <hi>keep</hi> his <hi>renewed Promiſes</hi> with <hi>Hereticks.</hi> (Poſſibly they thought his own Misfortunes might have taught him, if not better Faith, yet more of Government.) And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>none</hi> could either with <hi>ſafety</hi> of their Liberties, or even Lives, <hi>have proteſted.</hi> To have ſpoken againſt this Act, had been to have ſtruck at the Foundation of the Authority, not only of that (whatſoever it was of a) Parliament, jealous and tender enough be ſure of its own Power, but even of the whole Government of the Kingdom in all its Branches, And it was as clear as the Sun, ſuch perſon would have been either, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> by Vote of both Houſes executed for Treaſon; or if he had got out of the Protection of either Houſe, been forthwith <hi>De Witted,</hi> and torn in pieces by the Multitude.</p>
            <p>In a word, let this Recognition be of all the force and exactneſs imaginable to oblige us, it was extorted from us <hi>Vi et Dolo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo.</hi> And how far then it can oblige being ſatisfied in our own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, we will leave to any, who will be ſo juſt as to ſuppoſe themſelves to have been in our caſe, and to judge of us by their own ſenſe of themſelves, to paſs ſentence. We are ſure no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts, or Perſons learned in the Laws of God or Man, ſcarce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man of Reaſon or Conſideration, can condemn us.</p>
            <p>But give it what it had not, the <hi>Eſſence</hi> and <hi>Form of an Oath,</hi> aye, and ſuppoſe it <hi>not extorted:</hi> After all the <hi>ſame Procedure,</hi> as above, changing only the Term Oath of Allegiance into that of Recognition, <hi>diſſolves the Obligation</hi> of this as of the Other; for the Arguments are equally valid againſt both. Wherefore neither from this Recognition does there lie any Obligation upon us to <hi>James</hi> II.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Now laſtly, as to the <hi>Sacred Tye</hi> with which <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> binds all Oaths upon the Conſciences of Chriſtian people, that they are not to <hi>Inhabit the Holy Hill,</hi> or may not expect to go to Heaven, except when <hi>they ſweare even to their own hurt, they</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:153025:11"/> 
               <hi>change not,</hi> were it our own <hi>Temporal, Perſonal</hi> or <hi>Private Hurt</hi> that were concern'd, there had been ſome colour of Reaſon for us to have abode both by the Oaths and by the Recognition. We might, and perhaps moſt of us would have ventured the <hi>loſs</hi> of our <hi>Eſtates, Liberties</hi> and even <hi>Lives</hi> in a <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> (as in deed we have done, and actually ſuſteined the loſs, for no ſmall time, at leaſt of two of the three) had either we our ſelves, in our <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Perſons,</hi> been likely to have proved the ſole ſufferers, or had we been to have ſuffered only in our <hi>Outward Man.</hi> In a word, would <hi>ſelf-Denial</hi> and <hi>taking up our Croſs</hi> have ſolved the Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, we had eſteemed ſuch practice our Duty: And we can ſay without Vanity, we did really proceed therein, many times with chearfulneſs, in Imitation of, as well as Obedience to, our Bleſſed Lord; <hi>ſuffering patiently for well doing,</hi> as far as we could judge patient ſuffering lawful for us. But he who commanded us to Deny our ſelves, and take up our Croſs, did <hi>not command us to deſtroy our fellow Chriſtians</hi> and ruin our Poſterity; nor to <hi>cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</hi> with the <hi>corrupt,</hi> all <hi>natural</hi> affections. A man may indeed be conceived to have a right to diſpoſe of his Eſtate or Liberty, and in ſome caſes, or in ſome meaſure, of his Life by Honorable venturing of it: But however lawful it may be for a man to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh, enſlave, or caſt away himſelf, no man ſimply has right to diſpoſe of the Eſtates, Lives and Liberties of others: And thus ſtood affairs with us. It was not to our own or a ſingle mans hurt or two, that this Oath was wreſted and abuſed, but to the <hi>deſtruction of the whole body</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again in the duty of ſelf-denial, 'tis <hi>only</hi> the <hi>outward man</hi> or <hi>Temporal concerns</hi> that come within the verge of the precept; <hi>no wiſe our ſouls</hi> and everlaſting welfare. I am not commanded to damn my ſoul, through fidelity to any Oath; but I am rather to eſteem ſuch Oath a ſnare. Now it has been above made out, the Loyalty by this Oath claimed from us, was not conſiſtent with the common means of our Salvation; namely, not with the Enjoyment and Exerciſe of true Religion. But without the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Exerciſe of true Religion, People cannot ordinarily and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally attain unto Salvation. Except therefore Men can be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153025:12"/> bound to keep an Oath to the caſting away their own Souls, and the Souls of the generality of People, this Rule cannot be ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the preſent Caſe. Now this is ſo unreaſonable a thing to bind men to, as none but Madmen would expect it from any. Who would hear a Man exhorting at this rate; be conſtant to your Oath of Allegiance to your King, even to the abandoning the means of Salvation, and to virtual renouncing your God and Chriſtian Faith. Break your Dutiful Vow, which you have ſome hundred times iterated at the Communion, to keep an Oath once or twice ſworn to a purpoſe, and in a ſenſe, clear different to what it is now urged for. Perjure your ſelves to God, to be Loyal to your Perverted Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign. Damn your Souls to preſerve a Prince in the Abuſe of his Power. God deliver us from ſuch Arguing, and ſuch frantick <hi>Miſapplication</hi> of <hi>Scripture-Rules,</hi> as leads thereto.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. I ſhould here conclude upon the whole, but that I have frequently heard it, not without Inſolence and Scorn, demanded by more than a few, <hi>Where is now the Doctrine of Non reſiſtance and Paſſive Obedience?</hi> I anſwer, where it ever was: In our <hi>Bibles</hi> and in our <hi>Hearts;</hi> and I will add too, (not without Defiance to all who reproach us on this account) in our <hi>Practice</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>But this being a Gird from <hi>two ſorts</hi> of Men, ſome who <hi>upon the main are our Friends,</hi> and others <hi>altogether our profeſt Enemies,</hi> it muſt have an Anſwer diſtinctly accommodated to each.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. FIRST, to thoſe who though upon the main our Friends, yet ſeem to <hi>reject this Doctrine,</hi> upbraiding it of Novelty, and them, who taught it, of Court-Flattery, Compliance, Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, or ſome ſuch commendable Qualities, it is to be ſaid; tho ſome Men <hi>underſtand not</hi> this Duty, or have poſſibly <hi>misſtated</hi> the Doctrinal part of it, and others who have no mind to practice it, <hi>will not underſtand</hi> it to be their Duty, but perhaps ridicule it, yet <hi>in due Circumſtances a Chriſtian Duty it is,</hi> and muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged ſuch, till the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> (or words of Chriſt Jeſus) till the <hi>Epiſtles of St.</hi> Paul <hi>and St.</hi> Peter, as well as other Canonical Books, be torn out of our Bibles, or denied to be the Rule of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Morals. And I muſt add, as to our Caſe in particular;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153025:12"/> Had not the <hi>alwiſe Providence,</hi> and ſpecial Grace of our Heavenly Father, <hi>guided</hi> and governed the Hearts of ſome in this Kingdom to <hi>preach,</hi> and of many to <hi>practice</hi> this Duty, during theſe our two ſad laſt years, in which ſome of our Friends fled for their own ſafety, others perhaps were ignorant of our Condition, or much unable to help us (who (by the way) dearly earned their help, in ſtaying upon the ſpot to keep Poſſeſſion) there had ſcarce been <hi>a Proteſtant</hi> left <hi>in one half,</hi> I had almoſt ſaid in <hi>three parts of four,</hi> of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Beſides, we muſt be ſo free as to tell our Friends, it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered not only what <hi>ought,</hi> but what <hi>could</hi> be done by us. We were <hi>ſcattered</hi> throughout the Kingdom <hi>without a Head, and</hi> (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alas!) <hi>diſunited</hi> amongſt our ſelves; in moſt places, none of us could make ſo much as a fair Pretence to command one another, and in others, People would not obey ſuch as were fit or might claim ſome kind of right or color to command. We were obnoxious to, <hi>(what we felt)</hi> the <hi>frequent Invaſions</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> and the hourly <hi>Incurſions and Depredations of the Natives:</hi> 'tis uncertain which of the two more mercileſs: Furthermore, <hi>cut off from all Succors</hi> (which good God! how long with wearied and fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eyes, with ſinking Hearts did we look and groan for!) We can ſay, whatever Conſpiracy, Union or <hi>juncture of Circumſtances,</hi> may be conceived to make the duty of <hi>Non-reſiſtance more oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> ſeaſonable, and ſo <hi>more obligatory</hi> at one time than another, did occur in our the poor <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants Condition, who were under the power of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks. We had nothing left us to do, but what we did; firſt, to commit our Souls to God, and then yield our outward man and concerns, to what ſhould betide us, without fruitleſs (and to us certainly deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive) Struglings, and Exaſperations of our Enemies. We could thus <hi>heap Coals of Fire upon</hi> our Perſecutors <hi>Heads;</hi> that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps melt their otherwiſe relentleſs Hearts, ſoften their Temper, or exhauſt the <hi>impetus</hi> of their Cruelty. This way too, there was <hi>poſſibility of eſcaping;</hi> the other none. And this courſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, was next to the Divine Protection, <hi>our great Preſervative,</hi> and in our Condition, as far as we can yet ſee, the <hi>only one</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153025:13"/> I am ſure it was the <hi>only inducement</hi> or <hi>reaſonable Topic,</hi> which ſome of us, upon the utmoſt Conſideration, could find out to urge to our hard Maſters with hopes of ſucceſs for mercy. In a word, we by <hi>this Practice</hi> made up a <hi>Temper,</hi> and <hi>mixed</hi> (what our Saviour taught us in time of Perſecution to do) <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> with <hi>Innocence;</hi> and if ſome think us herein to have been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent, and others too credulous, we crave leave ſtill modeſtly and peaceably to diſſent: <hi>it is a very ſmall thing to us that we are judged of men:</hi> Touching our Honeſty, Sincerity, and through all our Sufferings, Conſtancy to God, to our common Religion and true Intereſt, (and I may add touching our Charity and upright Intentions to Mankind) we appeal to the Judgment of him who ſearcheth and ſeeth Hearts. I will, I need ſay no more to theſe our Friends.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. AS to the other ſort, who perhaps with us acknowledge [at leaſt, <hi>in Hypotheſi,] Paſſive Obedience</hi> to be a Duty, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe us, not only of the neglect of it, but of Preſumptions and wilful caſting it off, we avow, and ſtand to our avowry, <hi>we have practiſed it all along in its due latitude,</hi> and we adhere to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it at preſent. We have been and are conſtant to our ſelves, conſtant to our Faith and Duty. We never were, nor are we, of the number of thoſe, who cry up Abſolute Power, under a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick King, and exclaim againſt the Exerciſe of legal and qualified Power under Proteſtant Princes: who therefore ſhew, it is not any more true Loyalty, than true Religion (or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) that acts them, but Intereſt and blind Obedience dictate to them their Opinions, and then Faction or Bigottry governs their Practice; and that ſo ſlaviſhly, as not to ſuffer them to be impartial, in what yet for the general they approve. As to us, the Holy Word of God is our Rule, and Primitive Catholick Saints our Patterns and Examples: And from theſe we allow not our ſelves to ſwerve. Of <hi>Active Obedience,</hi> as far and as long, as with good Conſcience we could, we declined no part, as above profeſſed: When we could go no farther, or through the Suggeſtions of our Enemies, might not be truſted we <hi>quietly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153025:13"/> even to the enduring Oppreſſion it ſelf, in its very extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. In both regards, thus <hi>rendering unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things which are</hi> Caeſars. We could not ſerve in a War for the Deſtruction of the Proteſtant Religion: No more did the ancient Chriſtians againſt their fellow Chriſtians; and they are reputed Saints for it to this day, even in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: Witneſs the famous Caſe of <hi>St. Martin.</hi> There have been perhaps ſcarce in any days more illuſtrious <hi>Spectacles of Paſſive Obedience</hi> (The <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baean Legion</hi> being excepted) than ſome <hi>parts of Ireland</hi> have ſhewn within theſe <hi>fourteen or fifteen Months</hi> laſt paſt. Many hundreds of <hi>able,</hi> luſty, and well ſpirited Men, have rendred themſelves up in a body, at the cry of a Bell-Man, or ſome ſuch mean Summons, to a few People then in Power, whoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they would have ſcorned, had they not worn the moſt plauſible Character or Pretence (there was at that time in that part of the Kingdom) of legal and ordinary Authority. We can ſay, it was only <hi>through want of Commiſſion,</hi> that is, <hi>through mere Conſcience</hi> of want of due Authority on our ſides (which we now own our ſelves to have) that we ſuffered our ſelves (while we were ſenſible of our real Strength) to be <hi>driven in flocks</hi> to remote <hi>Priſons,</hi> (we knew not but) <hi>as Sheep to the ſlaughter;</hi> for not a few periſhed by or in Priſon. Mean while ſome poor Proteſtant Women, <hi>with their Sucking Children</hi> in their <hi>Arms,</hi> and <hi>at their Breaſts,</hi> have been <hi>knockt down,</hi> with the <hi>Butt ends of Muskets,</hi> for giving their hungry Husbands a bit of Bread in their Hands, as they paſſed by driven to Priſon. And I my ſelf, when complaining of this, have been told, <hi>This uſage was too good for us, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Viciſſitudes of Impriſonment and Oppreſſion, we <hi>Iriſh Proteſtants</hi> have ſuffered oftener than my Memory now or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps knowledge from the firſt ſerves to report. And theſe are <hi>ample Demonſtrations</hi> of our <hi>due regard</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtian Laws</hi> in this behalf.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153025:14"/> XVII. BUT ſome of theſe Gentlemen, whom we are now anſwering, may poſſibly further urge. However the quiet part of the <hi>Proteſtants in Ireland</hi> may not formerly have had <hi>ſo great a ſhare in Rebellion,</hi> as their <hi>Brethren in England,</hi> yet muſt they acknowledge <hi>thoſe their Brethren</hi> to have in the preſent Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution <hi>utterly caſt</hi> off the aforeſaid <hi>Doctrine and Practice:</hi> and themſelves now joyning with them, muſt needs become, if not equal, yet <hi>Partiſans</hi> in their Guilt, and conſequently be <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Apoſtates</hi> from their own avowed Principles.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer hereto, theſe great <hi>Patriots of Chriſtianity in Diſpute,</hi> but <hi>Enemies and Oppreſſors of it in Practice,</hi> muſt ſuffer us to tell them, (for it is no great preſumption to ſuſpect moſt of them, either through Infirmity, Wilfulneſs or Devotedneſs to a Party, <hi>ignorant)</hi> that <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> or <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtian Duties, has its <hi>Bounds, and Seaſons of Practice;</hi> and tho it be an undoubted Duty, obligatory to private perſons, and perhaps to ſome ſmall ſubordinate Societies of Men, yet does it not either concern all ſorts of Men, or all Bodies of People; much leſs whole Nations. It is not the Buſineſs of this Paper, to aſcertain all its Meaſures. But in ſhort: Who can imagine <hi>not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Evil, turning the other Cheek, giving the Cloak alſo,</hi> are Duties to be Preached to, or <hi>required of a Parliament?</hi> Can any be ſo abſurd, as to put no difference betwixt the private Rules of holy Living, and the publick Laws of Civil Government; betwixt means intended to bring penitent Men to Heaven, and thoſe deſigned to curb or reſtrain obſtinate wilful Sons of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that they deſtroy not the innocent and one another? For the attaining of one end, the great Meaſure to be obſerved, is Self-denial, and abundance of Charity; for the other, ſtrict Juſtice, and inſiſting upon particular Rights. On the one hand, in fit Circumſtances, Non Reſiſtance takes place as neceſſary; on the other, Reſiſtance, where other Means will not do, is no leſs neceſſary and lawful: So that what we ought, ordinarily, to teach a private handful of People to ſave their Souls, we muſt not dictate to the three Eſtates, to the Lords Spiritual and Temporal,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153025:14"/> together with the whole Commons aſſembled in Parliament (a Body of near eight hundred Perſons, all of higheſt Quality, in their reſpective Ranks and Orders, in the Kingdom) as a Standard, by which they are to regulate the State. <hi>What Senſe</hi> would it be to exhort them in Authority (and great is the Authority of the three Eſtates; when the King leaves the Nation, the greateſt certainly in the Nation) what Senſe would it be, I ſay, to preach to <hi>them in Authority,</hi> or <hi>to the higher Powers,</hi> to be <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to, and not reſiſt themſelves?</hi> But it is Senſe, and the <hi>Duty of the Clergy</hi> to <hi>diſſuade</hi> their People from <hi>Revenge,</hi> from <hi>multiplying Suits at Law,</hi> from <hi>Sedition, Tumults</hi> and <hi>rebellious Projects;</hi> and for this purpoſe to lay before them the Commands of the Goſpel, which require of them Peaceableneſs, Meekneſs, and rather to ſuffer Wrong, Damage, nay, even Oppreſſion it ſelf in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, than involve all in War and Blood, which is a far greater Oppreſſion: And this is all the Non-Reſiſtance we preach or hold. But whereas we are now involved in War, whoſe Fault is it? Theirs ſure who begun it, who firſt raiſed, and then main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained an Army contrary to Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In a word, and to ſpeak roundly, The <hi>King of England</hi> is <hi>King of three Kingdoms;</hi> by Law <hi>Proteſtants, not Slaves.</hi> It is <hi>impoſſible</hi> for three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms to have <hi>all their Eyes put out.</hi> They muſt therefore ſee themſelves ruining, before ruined. And it is as <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> as impoſſible, to <hi>perſuade three Kingdoms</hi> to give <hi>all their Throats to be cut.</hi> No Law of God, or Man, can be thought to oblige them hereto. For any therefore to think, that as the three Kingdoms ſee, ſo they ſhould not withſtand their own Ruin, or which is much the ſame, that the Duty of Non Reſiſtance ſhould take place in ſuch a Caſe as this, is for him to forfeit all Senſe and Reaſon, or to become really mad, that he may ſeem to be Religious. Wherefore when things have their true Names, either <hi>Engliſh or Iriſh Proteſtants</hi> taking <hi>Protection under a Proteſtant Prince,</hi> whoſe juſt Aſſertion of his own Rights neceſſarily involved alſo their Defence (and this at a time when their own King had caſt them off from Protection) muſt be acknowledged <hi>no Rebellion:</hi> I avow them who thus fly for, ſeek, or accept, Protection to be as Paſſive as any where the Goſpel requires them.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:153025:15"/> XVIII. BUT it will be ſaid, in reſpect of the <hi>Invaders,</hi> there muſt at leaſt be acknowledged an <hi>Offenſive War.</hi> Be it ſo, yet was it a moſt juſt one. For the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> was <hi>no Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> and therefore could <hi>not be a Rebel;</hi> and the Cauſes which he had to enter <hi>England,</hi> when he did, and in the manner in which he did, with armed Force, were both more in number, and for Weight and Juſtice far greater, than it can be expected ſhould be repreſented in this Paper. Nor was his Advancement to the Throne leſs juſt and equitable. I do not find that they, who have impartially conſidered all, can aſſign any thing that could be done, more <hi>reaſonable,</hi> and as far as Man can ſee, more <hi>wholeſome to the Intereſt of Religion</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> whether in the <hi>three Kingdoms,</hi> or even in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> it ſelf. But theſe things have been undoubtedly deduced by abler Hands; nor is it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to our preſent purpoſe any more than to point at them. <hi>We here</hi> have had a <hi>long and very dark night,</hi> and have been often <hi>abuſed with falſe Lights;</hi> ſo that perhaps we know not yet the true State of many Tranſactions, nor are capable therefore to diſcourſe of them, as were requiſite. <hi>Some perſons</hi> poſſibly there are, <hi>all whoſe Conduct</hi> I cannot <hi>excuſe:</hi> but the <hi>Swearing Faith</hi> to, or <hi>Praying</hi> for, <hi>King William or Queen Mary,</hi> does no wiſe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve</hi> any in a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of ſuch Mens <hi>Vindication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">XIX. THE Concluſion then of all ſhall be; Out of <hi>the Power of a King,</hi> which would not be perſwaded to preſerve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and neither could nor would protect his Proteſtant Subjects; Out of the <hi>Hands of mercileſs and barbarous Fellow-Subjects,</hi> who were bent to have deſtroyed both themſelves and their Country, and all in it with themſelves; and finally from the <hi>Laſhes of the Scourge of Chriſtendom,</hi> God has brought us poor oppreſſed Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants under a Proteſtant Prince. The <hi>Caſe</hi> now in ſhort is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>we will accept Protection</hi> or no? The <hi>Conditions</hi> indeed (ſay our Adverſaries) are very hard: Yes, they are no leſs than what <hi>God</hi> has <hi>made our Duty,</hi> if not our <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> to <hi>Swear to bear Faith,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:153025:15"/> and true Allegiance to, and <hi>to Pray for</hi> our <hi>Deliverers,</hi> and their <hi>Conquerors,</hi> in that Quality wherein we find them, and wherein they have Delivered us, and Conquered them. That is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſacredly to Man ſuch Subjection, and to make to God ſuch Prayers, which in our preſent Condition, even without ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, it were ſin not to do. In the whole Revolution God has not vouchſafed to us ſuch <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants (who are mainly concerned in this Paper) any active part in advancing theſe Princes to their Power: He has thought fit to aſſign us ſtill only a <hi>Paſſive Lot.</hi> We muſt acknowledge it is not, it has not been our Buſineſs to ſet up Powers: but yet we muſt own it is our Duty to obey them. And no leſs (certainly) to be thankful to God and them, if we may be protected by them. The Scripture is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher powers.</hi> Such cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the <hi>Conquerors are.</hi> And, <hi>I exhort, that firſt of all Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Prayers, Interceſſions, and giving of Thanks be made for all Men, for Kings, and all that are put in Authority;</hi> [even for the perſon of a <hi>Nero</hi> therefore at that time:] and if <hi>for the froward,</hi> much more <hi>for the good and gentle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us chearfully then comply in both points, and <hi>lay down</hi> not our <hi>Conquered Arms</hi> (for Arms we Proteſtants have not been now a long time ſuffered to wear,) but our <hi>captivated Hearts,</hi> at the <hi>Feet of</hi> King WILLIAM and Queen MARY, whom <hi>God long preſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND, <hi>O thou who haſt hitherto delivered us from our Enemies, Deliver us now from our ſelves. Let there be no</hi> Shimei <hi>or</hi> Sheba <hi>in our</hi> Iſrael: <hi>But bow thou the Hearts of all the Tribes as one Man, that they may eſtabliſh the Kingdom in their Majeſties, whom thy Hand and out ſtretched Arm has now ſet over us. Do thou, O King of Kings, defend theſe the true Defenders of the Faith, and make their Arms by Land and Sea Victorious, for the Reformation (if it might be thy Will) at leaſt for the Pacification of Chriſtendom; that we whom thou haſt ſaved from the Hands of</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153025:16"/> 
               <hi>our Enemies, may ſerve thee without fear, in Holineſs and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs before thee all the Days of our Life; and theſe Kingdoms may flouriſh, in Truth and Sanctity, in Peace amd Plenty, to the Glory of thy Name, and of the Bleſſed Memory of our Deliverers to all Poſterity:</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
